Blair and Lee Family Papers, 1640-1946 (bulk 1812-1920 ): Finding Aid C0614
Manuscripts Division
- Papers of Francis Preston Blair, 1640-1911; 1791-1876; 54 boxes (1 partial)
  - Papers of Others, 1640-1878; 14 boxes
    - Writings, 1640-1865; 5 boxes 7 folders
      - Contributions to the Globe, 1640-1858; 5 boxes
        - By Author, 1791-1858; 2 boxes 1 folder
          - G-H, 1831-1858; 1 folder (Box 36, Folder 5)
            Includes "Mr. Southard" by H.M. Garland (March 22, 1834), A. Gentzel (March 26, 1831), Gordon (undated), "Annals of Baltimore" by Thomas W. Griffith (undated), J.L.G. (undated), Carlos Hammer-ón (July 24, 1831), P.S.V. Hamot (February 5, 1839), Hinton Rowan Helper (November 15, 1858) Addison Hill (January 16, 1838), John Z. Hitch (May 1, 1834), [Joseph] Hopkinson (1837), and G.R. Hunter (July 1839).
          - I-J, 1831-1843; 1 folder (Box 36, Folder 6)
            Includes writings by Andrew Jackson (undated), Andrew Jackson (circa 1831), "Constitutionality of the Bank of the U.S. no. 1" by Andrew Jackson (undated), "[?] by Diplomacy" and "United States Bank" by George Jackson (undated), and James H.C. Johnson (August 26, 1843). Most of the Andrew Jackson writings do not appear to be in Jackson's hand.
          - K-L, 1834-1842; 1 folder (Box 36, Folder 7)
            Includes writings by George Kesling (June 23, 1841), L. Landers (undated), a fragment from Thomas Lawson (December 13, 1842), "How Richard M. Johnson" by John Lewis (February 23, 1837), "To the Public" by William B. Lewis (undated), Harry Lindsly (June 3, 1840), a fragment from John Lyon (undated), Johnston Lykins (September 21, 1834), and John W. Leod (undated).
          - Kendall, Amos, 1789-1869, 1832; 1 folder (Box 36, Folder 8)
            Includes "Our Minister in Colombia" (January 30, 1832), "An Error Explained" (undated), "The Late Cabinet" (undated), and two untitled letters (undated).
          - Lewis, S. L., 1839-1843; 1 folder (Box 36, Folder 9)
            Includes "Prejudice against Virginians securing office" (April 26, 1843) and "Review of the 'defined position' of Senator Rives" (1839).
          - M, 1831-1844; 1791-1855; 1 folder (Box 36, Folder 10)
            Includes writings by James Mcdowell (August 24, 1834), M. M. (August 1, 1831), B. McCaffrey (October 23, 1844), A.W. Maclean (October 21, 1844), Thomas M.S. McKennan (1838), McMell (undated), Madison (July 7, 1831), "[?] for a Prospectus," by J.L. Martin (undated), Joseph Martin (July 18, 1835), Virgil Maxcy (undated), James Might (March 9, 1831), Thomas P. Moore (September 18, 1834), "Objection to the Constitution U.S." by Colonel George Mason (undated), and transcriptions of writings by and about Chief Justice John Marshall (1791-1855).
          - N-O, 1831-1835; 1810-1835; 1 folder (Box 36, Folder 11)
            Includes a letter to the editor by John Norvell (August 13, 1831), J.M. Nab (September 15, 1835), "To the Honorable K. Polk, Chairman of the Commitee of Ways and Means," by Necker (February 24,1834), Richard N. Neveatt (undated), A.O.P. Nicholson (undated), John Milton Niles (undated), "Mr. Calhoun" by Christian Neck (undated), and "Remarks of Mr. Noland on the passage of the Bill to suppress Dueling" as transcribed from the Norfolk Gazette (1810).
          - P, 1832-1845; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 1)
            Includes writings by Daniel T. Patterson (undated), William Paxton (April 23, [1834]), Amos Peabody (September 6, 1836), W.R. Penn (October 16, 1838), "Elegy on the death of Mrs. Rachel Jackson" by Benjamin E. Phanes (November 15, 1833), Thomas H. Pitts (March 8, 1834 and June 2, 1832), "Mr. Burke's Repent" by E.R. Potter (January 11, 1845), "To the Natives of Fairfax," by John Powell (undated), "The Indians - Frontier Defenses," found with J.R. Poinsett (undated), "A Matrimonial Adventure [?]," by J.P. (undated), and "On the treatment of Cholera" by J. Parkin (July 1832).
          - Q, undated; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 2)
            Three untitled writings by the same author with the initials "O.P.Q."
          - R, 1831-1834; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 3)
            Includes writings by Philip Rainey (November 21, 1831), Jonathan J. Renner (undated), "A new song on an old subject" by Samuel Phillips Reynolds (February 10, 1834), Thomas Richmond (February 2, 1831), and James Ronaldson (undated).
          - S, 1831-1841; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 4)
            Includes writings by J. de Paula Santander (June 11, 1831), H.C. Scott (July 14, 1840), Robert Scrogin (January 16, 1832), "Voice of the South" by Jack Shackleford (undated), "Doty and the Sioux Treaty" by Jonathan P. Sheldon (circa 1841), "On Our Agriculture" by Joseph L. Smith (undated), Thomas Jefferson Smith (undated), W. Smith (undated), Baron Stackelberg (August 21, 1834), John C. Stone (June 5, 1834), "The Public Domain" (July 4, 1834) and "The President's Protest" (undated) by James Neal Swouga, and writings related to Judge Charles Shaler (1834-1835).
          - T, 1832-1841; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 5)
            Includes "To the Freemen of Maryland," by William S. Taneyhill (October 24, 1836), "The Prescriptive System- James H. Covens and the Patriot Clique," by John B. Taylor (July 20, 1841), [William] Terrell (undated), George Tenan (May 23, 1840), George Thomas (December 10, 1832), G. Thompson (undated), John Tipton (1836?), and "Leslie Combs" by George J. Trotter (September 1, 1832).
          - V-Z, 1832-1842; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 6)
            Includes writings by Samuel Van Camper (November 30, 1842), "Removal of the deposites" by Wallace (undated), Alphonso Wetmore (October 8, 1836), C.H.W. Wharton (July 9, 1832), John H. Wheeler (July 1, 1834), J. Williams (undated), R.H. William (September 30, 1837), R.K. Williams (undated), George F. Wilson (undated), and Levi Woodbury (undated).
          - Anonymous / Unidentified, 1829-1842; 7 folders
            - Anonymous / Unidentified, 1829-1832; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 7)
              Includes "Extract from a debate in the Virginia Convention" (1829), "To the People" (1832), and anonymous letters to the editor and corrections.
            - Anonymous / Unidentified, 1833-1834; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 8)
              Includes "Mr. Adams remarks on Heister petitions which were reformed" (1833), "Union of unpolluted Democracy - to the Emporer Nicholas & his Counsil" (February 22, 1834), "Statements of balances of Naval appropriations which remained in the Treasury on the first of September 1834," and anonymous writings and letters to the editor.
            - Anonymous / Unidentified, 1835-1839; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 9)
              Includes "Extract of a letter from a gentleman residing at Key West to his friend in this city" (January 15, 1839), and other anonymous or unidentified letters to the editor.
            - Anonymous / Unidentified, 1840-1842; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 10)
              Includes a poems titled "The Brave" (August 1841) and "Address to a Shinplaster" (June 24, 1841), an essay titled "Romancing" (1842, on Washington Irving), responses to articles published in other newspapers, anonymous letters to the editor, and a group of letters and essays from the same author, including those titled, "Sir Robert Peel...", "The New Secretary of State," and "The Glentworth Pamphlet of Mr Clay's 'Signal Victory'."
            - Anonymous / Unidentified, undated; 3 folders
              - Anonymous / Unidentified, undated; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 11)
                Includes writings titled "Chesapeake and Ohio Canal," "Natural Law and Crisis," "Consular System," "The Navy and 'Innez Barbor[?]' for old sailers," "A Patriot of the Revolution has fallen to the Tomb," "Aye stand erect - a Parody," "Superb Attraction," "The Mediterranean Squadron," "Pennsylvania," "What Shadows we are - and what Shadows we pursue" (Burke), "Long-Lately sung in this city at a recent meeting of the Cabal some time formed to dissolve the Union - by a prominent conspirator, with unbounded applause," "The Old Flannel Petticoat," "Declaration of Independence No. 2 by the inhabitants of the City of Washington" (Thomas Jefferson), "Remarks of a Foreigner in the United States - III. Laws and Time," "Great Attraction! W. Kennedy's Benefit!!," "Editorial remarks upon the 8th wonder from 'The Ohio Statesman'," "A Statement of allowances owed to Mr. Williams on the settlements of his accounts," "Public Lands," and "An act providing for the graduation and reduction of the price of the public lands."
              - Anonymous / Unidentified, undated; 1 folder (Box 37, Folder 12)
                Includes untitled writings and anonymous letters to the editor.
              - Anonymous / Unidentified, undated; 1 folder (Box 38, Folder 1)
                Includes untitled writings and letters to the editor.
        - By Topic, 1640-1843; 1 box 16 folders
          Arranged alphabetically by topic.
          - On the Abolition of Slavery, 1819-1835; 1 folder (Box 38, Folder 2)
            Includes a description of proceedings and vote count for a petition to abolish slavery in the District of Columbia (January 26, 1835), a document with notes about the abolition of slavery in various United States territories from 1819 to 1833, and Philip Doddridge's report on debates over the abolition of slavery (December 12, 1831).
          - On American Indians and American Indian Affairs, 1832-1840; 1 folder (Box 38, Folder 3)
            Includes writings titled "Black Hawk" and "Georgia Case" (April 1, 1832), an interrogation of Hiram Todd (July 1836), and anonymous writings and letters to the editor regarding Black Hawk, Pontiac, American Indian removal policies, colonization programs related to African Americans, and wars between white settlers and Native Americans, including writings about the Sauk, Creek, and Ottawa peoples.
          - On Banking Issues, 1831-1839; 4 folders
            - On Banking Issues, 1831-1839; 2 folders (Box 38, Folder 4-5)
              Includes anonymous writings and letters to the editor about the Second Bank of the United States. Printed materials include a supplement to the Globe (July 19, 1832) that contains President Andrew Jackson's veto message regarding the Bank Bill, a circular titled "Resolutions Passed at the Great Meeting of the Friends of the Administration and Opponents to the United States Bank, at Faneuil Hall, March 14, 1834," and a copy of Bill S. 40 (24th Congress, 2nd Session) regarding the removal of deposits from the United States Bank (1836). There are also writings titled "A Sketch of the Treasury System" (1837), "Statements regarding the judgement of the Supreme Court of the State of Louisiana in the case of the Bank v. Lawson" (June 22, 1837), "Federal Bank Celebrations in Georgetown, D.C.," "United States Bank - A Text of the Intelligencer, United States, and National Gazettes," "Benedict Arnold and Mordecai the Jew: A Parallel," "To the Honorable William L. May," "Governor Campbell's Message," "Contract of Public Money," "State of the Case," and "Bank of the United States."
            - On Banking Issues, undated; 2 folders (Box 38, Folder 6-7)
              Includes writings titled "Bank facilities for land speculators," "A Voice from Ohio," "Communication to the Senate on March 2nd, 1811" ("Clay's report against allowing time to the Bank"), "Turning to Clay," "Bankrupt Law," "Of Public Moneys in Ohio and Indiana," "The Treasury Order," "The Senate's Bank Committee," "Artificial Security and High Prices," "U.S. Bank Stock," "Bank United States," "Bank of the United States," "Evils of the Banking System," "An Address on Paper Money," "Demand of the Bank upon Government," "The True Issue," "Office Holders," "New York Journal of Commerce," "The Albany Regency," "The Divorce," and other anonymous writings and letters to the editor.
          - On Congress, 1832-1842; 2 folders (Box 39, Folder 1-2)
            Includes a statement from Amos Lane (April 20, 1836), "Proceedings on abolition in 1828 and 1829, with extracts from Alexander's report," "Poindexter's Resolution," "Motion submitted by Mr. Poindexter," "Extract from Mr. Clay's speech in reply to General Hayne" (February 1832), "Mr. Ritchie and his influence" (August 10, 1832), "Senate Journal - Synopsis of the abolition question in the Senate" (1836), "Pickney's Resolution" (1836), "To Mr. Slade, M.C. from Vermont" (March 28, 1840), "A thank you for Mr. Duncan's speech" (April 10, 1840), "Mr. Poindexter and Mr. Moore of the Senate, and M. M. Noah and James Nathan Webb," "About Bouldin and Rives of Va.," "Mr. Poindexter and his writings," "Extract of a letter from a distinguished gentleman of Virginia, of the old republican school on the President's protest," "Extract of a letter from a Gentleman of Virginia," "Mr. Clay and Mr. Webster," "Mr. Hill," and "Mr. Ward's Speech on the 4th of July Celebration." Also includes anonymous letters and drafts of articles, including writings about various members of Congress, including Senators Henry Clay and George Poindexter, letters directed at members of Congress, a eulogy for Judge William R. King, and an account written by James Blair of the nomination of S.D. Hays as Surveyor General of Public Lands.
          - On Congressional Printing, 1831-1836; 1 folder (Box 39, Folder 3)
            Contains various writings and extracts regarding congressional printing, including one titled "Extract from N.P.T. to Mr. Madison."
          - On John C. Calhoun, 1825-1833; 1 folder (Box 39, Folder 4)
            Contains various writings and letters to the editor about John C. Calhoun, including those titled "Mr. Calhoun - and his new Deputy Mr. Dole," and "Vice President and his correspondence," among others.
          - On the Currency, 1831-1837; 1 folder (Box 39, Folder 5)
            Includes writings titled "The opinion of a Western gentleman of distinguish and talents on the President's late Treasury Order requiring... of public lands" (February 21, 1837), "Banks without Bank notes," "The Specie Order," "Branch Mints," "Sound Currency," "Supression of Small Notes," "Remarks on the speech of Mr. Webster in Congress on Currency" (November 1837), "Suppression of Specie Payments," and "Currency or Money," along with other untitled writings and anonymous letters to the editor.
          - On Duff Green, Editor of The Telegraph, 1832; 1 folder (Box 39, Folder 6)
            Includes writings titled "The Extra Telegraph," "Hear any talk of wool?," "Mr. Monroe and the Telegraph," "The Infamous Globe," "A Series of Articles on Duff Green on Telegraph Style," and "Duff Green's Predictions," along with anonymous letters to the editor.
          - On Elections, 1831-1834; 2 folders (Box 39, Folder 7-8)
            Includes writings titled "To the Honorable John M. Patton," "Anecdote," "The Verdict of the people on the New Jersey Congressional election," "To the People of the United States - The Presidential Election I-VII" by Patrick Henry (February 1836), "To Philip P. Barbour, Esquire," "War, Pestilence and Famine," and "Tories!!," meeting minutes from a Democratic Republican Meeting taken by Alonzo Cressy, and various untitled writings, extracts, and letters to the editor.
          - On Foreign Relations, undated; 1 folder (Box 39, Folder 9)
            Consists of an essay titled "Sketch of New Granada," an essay about the Belgian legation, and a copy of a report by United States Ambassador to Spain George W. Erving.
          - On France, 1832-1834; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 1)
            Includes several anonymous writings, extracts, and letters to the editor regarding France, including an essay titled "Washington and Bonaparte" and a bound collection of extracts of articles from other newspapers including the Intelligencer, the U.S. Telegram, the Philadelphia Gazette, the Boston Daily Advertiser, and the Baltimore Chronicle (December 4-16, 1834).
          - On the Globe, 1831-1832; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 2)
            Includes an address titled "New Year's Address" and several anonymous letters to the editor.
          - On Great Britain, 1836-1840; 1640-1840; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 3)
            Includes extracts titled "From the Journals of the House of Commons / From the Journals of the House of Lords" (1641-1768, transcribed later), "From the United Service Journal" (London, February 1836), and "History of British India Vol. III pages 56, 57"; writings titled "The Working Class of Great Britain," "Balance of Trade" (April 5, 1832), "Settlement of Accounts," "Lord Melbourne and Mrs. Norton" (circa 1836), "England," "Ship Money," and "The Boundary Question;" along with other calculations and writings.
          - On Andrew Jackson and His Administration, 1801-1838; 2 folders (Box 471, Folder 4-5)
            Includes writings and extracts titled "Reform Advocated," "Philosophical Miscellanies..." (1838), "Reasons Against Jacksonism and ways to prove or disprove them," "Born to Command," "Stronger than the Strongest," "Signs of the Times," "Ode Written for the Celebration of the 4th of March, 1828" by Harriet Gouch[?], "General Jackson North and South No. II," an extract by Thomas Butler from the National Intelligencer (1814-1815), and "The President's House," D. L. Barringer's account of Andrew Jackson's conversation with Colonel Danforth (April 1832), an untitled essay by Alexander Hunter, copies of indentures (1801), and anonymous writings, lists, and letters to the editor.
          - On Martin Van Buren, 1832-1836; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 6)
            Includes a document titled "Conversation with the President" (February 24, 1832) and other anonymous writings, extracts, and letters to the editor.
          - On Nullification, 1833-1842; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 7)
            Includes writings and extracts titled "The Union it must be preserved" (March 2, 1837), "On Nullifaction: The Old man and his Sons," "Parallel Cases," "A Horizontal Tariff," "The Crisis No. 1 - To the Freemen of Maryland," "The Effects of Duties upon the importing of Foreign Manufactures" (Babbage), "Pennsylvania to South Carolina," and other anonymous writings and letters to the editor.
          - On Religion, 1831-1832; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 8)
            Includes writings titled "General Jackson's Religious Opinions" (September 1, 1832), "A Letter to the Rev. Dr. Brownlee and the Rev. George Bourne of New York," and "To Jews in North America, particularly those now residing in the United States, and their territories," and several other anonymous writings and letters to the editor.
          - On the Resignation of Jackson's Cabinet, 1831; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 9)
            Consists of several anonymous writings and letters to the editor.
          - On the Whig Party, 1834-1843; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 10)
            Includes writings and extracts titled "Whigs and Tories" (September 1, 1834), "The St. Louis Whig Celebration of the Battle of Fort Meigs" (May 5, 1840), "Log! Cabins!! Hard Cider!!! Koon Skins!!!!," "Harrison Reform in Florida," "Incantation for a Whig Election from the rear Melodrama of the 'Hard Cider Suckers'," "Choice Extracts from Whig Chronicles," "I would not be a Whig," "Notes of a conversation with Col. Croghan," "The Whigs of 1834," "The Richmond Whig," and "Mr. Webster's Letter to [?], communicated by a Whig" (1840), and other anonymous writings and letters to the editor. Includes articles about the William Henry Harrison and John Tyler administrations.
        - Lists of Newspapers, undated; 1 folder (Box 471, Folder 11)
      - Eaton, John Henry, 1790-1856, circa 1830-1831; 1 folder (Box 44, Folder 1)
        Consists of a partial manuscript draft (pages 8-14) of a long tract regarding various offenses and rifts between John Henry Eaton (1790-1856) and other members of Andrew Jackson's Kitchen Cabinet. In the tract, Eaton accuses his fellow Cabinet members of slander, as well as of excluding him from the Cabinet.
      - Ingersoll, Charles Jared, 1782-1862, undated; 1 folder (Box 44, Folder 2)
        Consists of a manuscript list of recommendations regarding arrangements for a proposed publication titled The Washington Review.
      - McCalla, John Moore, 1793-1873, circa 1830s; 1 folder (Box 44, Folder 3)
        Manuscript essay regarding General William Orlando Butler.
      - Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849, circa 1836; 1 folder (Box 44, Folder 4)
        Includes an essay titled "The Previous Question" and related notes regarding debates over the abolition of slavery in the District of Columbia, along with other loose notes.
      - Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862, circa 1857; 1 folder (Box 44, Folder 5)
        Manuscript comments on the Election of 1856.
      - Woodbury, Levi, 1789-1851, undated; 1 folder (Box 44, Folder 6)
        Includes a manuscript essay titled "The Vice Presidency" and an untitled manuscript essay fragment.
      - Unidentified Writings, 1865; 1 folder (Box 44, Folder 7)
        Includes an essay titled "Ashes, Not fire, in the 'Southern Heart'" (March 12, 1865) and undated notes titled "Bentonian queries to [?]"
    - Correspondence, 1799-1878; 3 boxes 10 folders
      Contains correspondence between Blair family members, political figures, and people associated with the Globe.
      - Unidentified writers, 1831-1834; 1 folder (Box 40, Folder 1)
      - A - B, 1830-1866; 1 folder (Box 40, Folder 2)
      - Blair Family, 1831-1878; 1 box 10 folders
        - Blair, Apolline (Mrs. F. P., Jr.), 1843-1873; 4 folders
          - Blair, Apolline (Mrs. F. P., Jr.), Letters Received, 1863-1873; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 1)
          - Blair, Apolline (Mrs. F. P., Jr.), Letters to Andrew A. Blair, undated; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 2)
          - Blair, Apolline (Mrs. F. P., Jr.), Letters to Mrs. F. P. Blair, Sr, 1843-1873; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 3)
          - Blair, Apolline (Mrs. F. P., Jr.), Letters to F. P. Blair, Jr, 1862-1865; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 4)
        - Blair, Eliza Violet Gist (Mrs. F. P., Sr.) - Memorabilia, letters received and sent, 1831-1876; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 5)
        - Blair, Elizabeth, Letters received, 1862; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 6)
        - Blair, Francis P., Jr., 1835-1873; 6 folders
          - Blair, Francis P., Jr., Letters received A - N, 1841-1873; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 7)
          - Blair, Francis P., Jr., Letters received R - W, 1848-1867; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 8)
          - Blair, Francis P., Jr., Letters sent, 1836-1872; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 9)
          - Blair, Francis P., Jr., Letters to Apolline Blair, 1855-1865; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 10)
          - Blair, Francis P., Jr., Letters to Mrs. F. P. Blair, Sr., 1835-1862; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 11)
          - Blair, Francis P., Jr., Letters to Montgomery Blair, 1844-1873; 1 folder (Box 42, Folder 12)
        - Blair, James: Letters received, 1833; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 1)
        - Blair, James Lawrence (1819-1853): Letters sent, 1844-1857; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 2)
        - Blair, James Lawrence (1819-1853): Letters received, 1835-1852; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 3)
        - Blair, Minna (Mrs. Montgomery): Letters received, undated; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 4)
        - Blair, Montgomery, 1833-1878; 5 folders
          - Blair, Montgomery, Letters sent, 1837; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 5)
          - Blair, Montgomery, Letters received A - L, 1836-1878; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 6)
          - Blair, Montgomery, Letters received M - W, 1836-1878; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 7)
          - Blair, Montgomery, Letters to Mrs. F. P. Blair, Sr., 1833-1846; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 8)
          - Blair, Montgomery, Letters to F. P. Blair, Jr., 1836-1862; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 9)
        - Blair, William Alexander - Letters sent, 1877; 1 folder (Box 43, Folder 10)